Inventory of the Brown, Coalter, Tucker Papers (I) 1780-1929
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Group B: Capt. Henry Brown and Brown Family Papers, 1774-1848., 7 boxes. (Box 7-13)
  - Correspondence of the immediate family of Capt. Henry Brown, including letters from his brothers, his daughters, and their respective spouses, 1797-1841., 81 items. (Box 12:1-69)
    - Mrs. Alice [Brown Worthington], Richmond and Georgetown, to Henry Brown, March-June 1839., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 12:51)
      The youngest daughter of Henry Brown writes about her marriage and the first meeting with her new relatives.
    - William Brown (son of Samuel), Staunton, to Henry Brown, 25 April 1839. (Box-folder 12:52)
    - W. W. Worthington, Richmond, to Henry Brown, 15 June 1839. (Box-folder 12:53)
      On his marriage to Alice Brown.
    - Mrs. A[lice B.] Worthington, Cincinnati, to her sister Mrs. Alexander [Lockie T. Brown] Irvine, 14 November 1839. (Box-folder 12:54)
      Her wedding trip to New Orleans.
    - Mrs. A. B. Worthington, New Orleans, to Henry Brown, 12 December 1839. (Box-folder 12:55)
      Her sickness on the way down the river due to fresh paint in the boat.
    - Daniel Brown (son of Samuel), Laporte, Indiana, to Alexander Irvine, 25 December 1839. (Box-folder 12:56)
    - Rev. James Mitchell Setter to Henry Brown, n.d. (Box-folder 12:57)
      Concerning eventual conversion of Baptists to the Presbyterian Church.
    - Mrs. Frances [B. Robinson] to her father, Henry Brown, 8 January [1840]. (Box-folder 12:58)
    - Mrs. Alice (Brown) W[orthington] at Georgetown to Henry Brown, 20 April [1840]., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 12:59)
      "...I left New Orleans the 28th of March and reach G[eorge].T[own]. The 15th of April...Sam (Brown) was in New Orleans the day before I left-he was not married but expected to be the 9th of April."
    - W. W. Worthington, Georgetown, to Henry Brown, 17 July 1840. (Box-folder 12:60)
      "Last evening our darling Alice made me the happy father of a fine boy..."
    - Mrs. Alice Worthington, Georgetown, to Henry Brown, 8 May 1841. (Box-folder 12:61)
    - Three undated items: Account of Samuel White with Witt and Dow, "Definition of Oratory," and "Breathing," n.d. (Box-folder 12:62-63)
    - E. J. Steptoe, West Point, to Dr. Wm. Steptoe at New London, 10 December 1833. (Box-folder 12:64)
      Report to his father of his first grades at the Academy.
    - E. J. Steptoe, West Point, to Henry Brown, 25 January 1834. (Box-folder 12:65)
      To his grandfather regarding his first term marks.
    - E. J. Steptoe, West Point, to his stepmother and father, November 1834., 3 items. ALS. (Box-folder 12:66)
      "The first two years of our course are exclusively devoted to Mathematics and French..." Encloses a work sheet and "Synopsis of the Course of Studies at the Military Academy."
    - E. J. Steptoe, Oklawaka River and St. Augustine, Flordia, to Dr. Wm. Steptoe, January-February 1838., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 12:67)
      "The Congress must get rid of its 'sickly sympathy' (with the Indians) or, rely upon it, this is a war of years to come." Gives a vivid description of St. Augustine.
    - E. J. Steptoe, Rose's Landing, Tennessee; Savannah, Georgia; and off Cape Hatteras, July-November 1838., 3 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 12:68)
      Contrasts the Cherokees in Tennessee with the Seminoles of Florida. Describes Savannah in a letter enclosed, dated February 16, 1839.
    - Typescript copies of letters of E. J. Steptoe. 1826-1838., 8 letters. Total of 12 pages. Typescript. (Box-folder 12:69)
    Subseries 3: Children of Capt. Henry Brown
  - Children of Capt. Henry Brown - Letters of Henry Brown, Jr. and Samuel T. Brown, 1822-1856., 128 items. (Box 13:1-71)
    Letters of Henry Brown, Jr., oldest son of Capt. Henry Brown; Samuel Thompson Brown, youngest son; and other members of the immediate family.
    Henry Brown, Jr., who suffered a grave illness in 1822 as a result of which he almost lost his eyesight, went into the partnership of his father with Amman Hancock. In 1835-1836, he opened his own store in Lynchburg, but died in May 1836, while on a buying trip to New York. Interesting items in this part of the collection include a 44 page book of mineral and chemical notes (31 July 1826), a 56 page diary kept by Henry Brown, Jr. on his trip abroad (24 July 1831), drafts of letters by Henry Brown, Jr. to newspapers regarding horses, and instructions for horse care, and the like (13 April 1835-March 1836). The will of Henry Brown, Jr. (May-December 1830), and his deathbed statement dictated to his wife (May 1836), are also included.
    The papers of Samuel Thompson Brown include the card which announced the opening of his law office in Bedford (8 May 1838), records of his marriage in Alabama (27 April 1840), and the death of his wife within the year (3 April 1841). A letter of 22 January 1842, mentions the business failures taking place in Richmond and Lynchburg, and one of 27 August of the same year comments on the national political situation which is "sadly out of joint." In a letter of 20 September [1845], there is a report of "the thefts which were perpetrated by Thomas H. Benton whilst a student at Chapel Hill."
    - Henry Brown, Jr., White Sulphur Springs, to his father, Capt. Henry Brown, 9 July 1822. (Box-folder 13:1)
      "My eyes appear to have improved gradually." (His ailment seemed to be at its worst at this time, though he continued to suffer from the ailment until his death in 1836 at the age of 39 years.)
    - Henry Brown, Jr. to Henry Brown, [1823]. (Box-folder 13:2)
    - Henry Brown, Jr., to Farmer's Bank of Virginia, 4 June 1824. (Box-folder 13:3)
      A note for $1000.00. At this time he was getting started in the store, Hancock and Brown Co.
    - Henry Brown, Jr., White Sulphur Springs, to Henry Brown, 9 August 1824. (Box-folder 13:4)
    - Henry Brown, Jr., Lynchburg, to Henry Brown, [1825]. (Box-folder 13:5)
    - Henry Brown, Jr. to Henry Brown, 27 February [1826]. (Box-folder 13:6)
      The "most favorable accounts" of John Thompson Brown from the members of the House of Delegates.
    - Henry Brown, Jr., Lynchburg, to Henry Brown, 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 13:7)
      Concerning the business of Col. [Mark] Anthony, in which Henry Brown, Jr. appears to be involved.
    - Court cost vouchers, of Sam Clayton vs. Mark Anthony, March 1826., 2 items. ADS. (Box-folder 13:8)
    - Henry Brown, Jr. Mineral and chemical notes, etc., 31 July 1826., 44 pages. (Box-folder 13:9)
    - Successive wills of Henry Brown, Jr., 22 May, 29 July, 25 December 1830., 3 items. ADS. (Box-folder 13:10)
    - Henry Brown, Jr., Lynchburg, to Henry Brown., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 13:11)
      Mentions the marriage of John Thompson Brown.
    - J. Burton Harrison, Lynchburg, to Monsieur Niles, in Paris, 21 July 1831. (Box-folder 13:12)
      A letter of introduction for Henry Brown, Jr., for use on his trip to England and the Continent in that year.
    - Travel notebook of Henry Brown, Jr., 24 July 1831., 56 pages. (Box-folder 13:13)
    - Mrs. Eleanor C. L. Brown to her husband, Henry Brown, Jr. on his trip, October-November 1831., 3 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 13:14)
      "Oh, my dear husband, why was it that I did not accompany you?" (None of these letters reached Henry Brown, Jr. on the trip, but followed him home).
    - Mrs. Eleanor C. L. Brown to Henry Brown, [October] 1831. (Box-folder 13:15)
      News from a letter she received from Henry Brown, Jr. in England.
    - George Tucker, University [of Virginia], to Henry Brown, Jr., January 1832., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 13:16)
      Payment of his debts in Lynchburg; hiring out of a slave.
    - Henry Brown, Jr. to Mrs. Eleanor C. L. Brown, 8 December 1832. (Box-folder 13:17)
      "it's really a sad case for me, to be sick from home and away from all that (are) Dear to me..."
    - Accounts of Samuel T. Brown, in account with Hancock and Brown, 3 April 1833., 4 items. AD. (Box-folder 13:18)
      This was the store in Lynchburg in which Henry Brown was a partner and with which Henry Brown, Jr. was associated until he opened his own store in 1835.
    - Henry Brown, Jr., Lynchburg, to Henry Brown, May 1834., 3 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 13:19)
      Brother-in-law, Jack [Willcox]; his brother, John's speech on the Petersburg Rail Road; and the house that Henry Brown has vacated in Lynchburg.
    - Henry Brown, Jr., Deerwood, to Henry Brown, [1834]. (Box-folder 13:20)
      On a debt of Thomas Williams.
    - Letters, advertisements etc. concerning horses, 1835., 18 items. (Box-folder 13:21)
    - Letter to "Mssrs. Editors," concerning Virginia geological formations, [1835]. (Box-folder 13:22)
    - Lists and memoranda, [1835]., 2 items. ADr. (Box-folder 13:23)
      Appear to refer to pictures, and may date from the time of one of the buying trips that Henry Brown, Jr. made with his wife.
    - "Henry Brown, Jr.," February 1836. (Box-folder 13:24)
      After breaking from the partnership of Hancock and Brown, he opened his own store.
    - Henry Brown, Jr., Lynchburg, [March] 1836., ALS. Cover lost. (Box-folder 13:25)
      Concerning the care for his horses, Young American Eclipse and Spring Hill, while he is away.
    - Mrs. Eleanor C. L. Brown, Philadelphia and New York, to Capt. Henry Brown, April-May 1836., 3 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 13:26)
      Written while she and her husband were on a buying trip for the Lynchburg store. In New York Henry Brown, Jr. was taken desperately ill and died.
    - Deathbed statement of Henry Brown, Jr., unsigned and undated, [May] 1836. (Box-folder 13:27)
      Evidently taken down by Mrs. Eleanor C. L. Brown during the final days in New York.
    - K. B. Townley, Lynchburg, to Samuel L. Brown, July, October 1836., 3 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 13:28)
      An associate of Henry Brown, Jr. in the Lynchburg store, was liquidating the stock and selling horses in order to settle the estate.
    - Profile to accompany the Geological Reconnoisance of the State of Virginia by Prof. Wm. B. Rogers, 1836. (Box-folder 13:29)
    - Capt. Henry Brown in account with the estate of Henry Brown, Jr., 7 January 1837. (Box-folder 13:30)
    - Samuel T. B[rown] to Henry Brown, 3 May 1837. (Box-folder 13:31)
      A note regarding the settlement of the Henry Brown, Jr. estate.
    - Henry Guilford Brown, Brownsburg, to his mother, Mrs. Eleanor C. L. Brown, August 1837. (Box-folder 13:32)
      Written from school, with endorsement by James Morrison, schoolmaster.
    - "A Description of the Departure of some of the Pilgrims for the Celestial City (vide Pilgrims Progress)," [1837]. (Box-folder 13:33)
      Signed Eleanor C. L. Brown.
    - Calling card of Samuel T. Brown, Attorney, 8 May 1838. (Box-folder 13:34)
    - Mrs. Eleanor C. L. Brown to her son, H. Guilford Brown, 24 May 1838. (Box-folder 13:35)
    - Sam. H. Garland, Lynchburg, to Samuel T. Brown, 25 May 1838. (Box-folder 13:36)
    - E[dward] L. Steptoe, Fort Payne, Alabama, to Samuel T. Brown, 28 July 1838. (Box-folder 13:37)
    - Charge slips to Samuel T. Brown for failing to attend army musters between 1829 and 1839, 1839., 10 items. PDS. (Box-folder 13:38)
    - W. W. Worthington, New Orleans, to his brother-in-law, Samuel T. Brown, 27 April 1840. (Box-folder 13:39)
      Congratulating S. T. B. on his marriage.
    - Mrs. Mary E. Brown, Walnut Hill, to her sister-in-law, Mrs. Alexander Irvine, 22 June 1840. (Box-folder 13:40)
      Writes of the aged John Vaughan Willcox, her father, with whom she is living and for whom she is caring; Samuel T. Brown and his "youthful bride."
    - Draft of a statement of Henry Brown and Samuel T. Brown to Micajah Davis, Jr., concerning the estate of Henry Brown, Jr., 3 November 1840. (Box-folder 13:41)
    - Samuel T. Brown, Louisville, to his father, Henry Brown, 15 November 1840. (Box-folder 13:42)
      His extended wedding trip; description of Gen Harrison's house.
    - Court cost voucher recording transfer of 400 acres from Henry Brown to Samuel T. Brown, with tax receipt, 1840., 2 items. PDS. (Box-folder 13:43)
    - Angile Ede Vendit, Spring Hill, to Mrs. Caroline C. [Samuel T.] Brown, 28 January 1841. (Box-folder 13:44)
    - A. Henry to Miss Mary Nicholson, care of Judge Crawford at St. Stephens, Alabama, 3 April 1841. (Box-folder 13:45)
      Consolations upon the death of Mrs. Samuel T. Brown.
    - Letters received by Susan Crawford, St. Stephens, Alabama, May-June 1841., 3 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 13:46)
    - J. E. Sawyer, Greensboro, to Samuel T. Brown, May-June 1841., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 13:47)
      Condolences upon the death of Mrs. Samuel T. Brown.
    - Mrs. Alice [Brown] Worthington to her brother, Samuel T. Brown, 19 May 1841. (Box-folder 13:48)
      A letter of consolation.
    - S. Mordecai, Mobile, to [Samuel Brown], 8 June 1841. (Box-folder 13:49)
    - Mrs. Frances [Brown] Robinson to her brother, Samuel T. Brown at St. Stephens, Alabama, 22 January 1842. (Box-folder 13:50)
    - Ed. Robinson, Baltimore, to Samuel T. Brown, February-April 1842., 5 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 13:51)
      On the death of W. W. Worthington, brother-in-law of Samuel T. Brown. "Your sister Alice is desirous of your attention to the affairs of Mr. W. in New Orleans prior to your return to Virginia."
    - [Judge] Wm. Crawford, St. Stephens, Alabama, to Wm. Grimes, Clerk of the County Court of Washington, 10 March 1842. (Box-folder 13:52)
      Recording certain deeds for his son-in-law, Samuel T. Brown.
    - J. E. Sawyer, Greensboro, Louisiana, to Samuel T. Brown, New London, Virginia, 27 August 1842. (Box-folder 13:53)
    - Samuel T. Brown(?). Unsigned and undated draft, n.d. (Box-folder 13:54)
      Written to his overseer with whom he has quarreled.
    - Alice Worthington, Richmond, to Samuel T. Brown, 3 January 1843. (Box-folder 13:55)
    - E. Patterson to Samuel T. Brown, 29 September 1843. (Box-folder 13:56)
    - T. W. F. Crawford, St. Stephens, Alabama, to Samuel T. Brown, 14 October 1843. (Box-folder 13:57)
    - Virginia Pegrune, Richmond, to Mrs. Mary E. Brown, 13 February 1845., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 13:58)
    - E. Irvine, Rocky Mount, Virginia, to Samuel T. Brown, 20 September 1845. (Box-folder 13:59a)
      On the fees paid by Henry Brown in the Leftwich case: "between twenty and twenty-five dollars for my services as an attorney." On the thefts "perpetrated by Thomas H. Benton whilst a student at Chapel Hill."
    - Agreement between Beverage Hughes and David Wright for the payment of a debt, 23 September 1845. (Box-folder 13:59b)
    - Samuel T. Brown. Drafts of a letter to Mark Andrews, [August] 1847., 2 items. ADrS. (Box-folder 13:60)
      Concerning the cutting of trees on the property of Samuel T. Brown.
    - M. Andrews to Samuel T. Brown. 31 August 1847. (Box-folder 13:61)
      A reply to the above letter, Box-Folder 13:60.
    - Mrs. Alice Worthington to her brother, Samuel T. Brown, 17 February 1848. (Box-folder 13:62)
    - Receipt to Samuel T. Brown from Broods and Bell, 13 May 1848. (Box-folder 13:63)
    - Wm. T. Yancey, Lynchburg, to Samuel T. Brown, 30 October 1848. (Box-folder 13:64)
      On a charge of Ammon Hancock against the estate of Henry Brown, Jr.
    - [Samuel T. Brown] to Alice [Worthington], 20 December 1848. (Box-folder 13:65)
    - J. H. Hopkins, Richmond, to Edwin Robinson, 12 March 1849. (Box-folder 13:66)
      Estimate for the cost of the construction of a bridge.
    - Receipt to Samuel T. Brown for postal expenses, April-June, 1849, signed H. Stevens, 29 June 1849. (Box-folder 13:67)
    - August Leftwich, Lynchburg, to Samuel T. Brown, July-October 1849., 4 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 13:68)
      On the property in Mobile, Alabama, purchased by Samuel T. Brown.
    - W. H. Haxable, Richmond, to Samuel T. Brown, July-November 1849., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 13:69)
    - W. H. Haxable, Richmond, to Samuel T. Brown, March-April 1850., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 13:70)
    - Edward Robinson, Richmond, to his brother-in-law, Samuel T. Brown, February-March 1856., 3 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 13:71)
      The sale of a female slave "with her Brood."
  Series 3: Group C
- Group C: John Thompson Brown Papers, 1816-1839., 6 boxes. (Box 14-19)
  Papers concern John Thompson Brown's attendance at Princeton, study of law, and trips to the South and to the West Indies. Includes speeches and correspondence as well as his published writings (newspaper articles, bills and pamphlets). The collection emphasizes his political career in the Virginia House of Delegates including his views on slavery. Also includes architectural plans for a two room house and elevations (1827), drafts of toasts and letters concerning his fight with John Hampden Pleasants.
  Prominent correspondents include William Segar Archer, James Murray Mason, John Hampden Pleasants, William Cabell Rives, Henry St. George Tucker and John Tyler.
  - Box 14 - Papers of John Thompson Brown, son of Capt. Henry Brown; attendance at New London Academy; of his schooling at Princeton (1817-1820); his travels to the West Indies; his legal training under Judge Creed Taylor; arid his trip to Clarksburg, where he set up practice. Also bound scrapbook of his letters printed in newspapers, and speeches made in the General Assembly of Virginia, 1816-1832., 62 items. (Box-folder 14:1-30)
    John Thompson Brown (1802-1836) was born at Otter Hills, near Bedford, Virginia and was the son of Henry Brown (1760-1841). He attended the New London Academy, 1816; studied at Princeton, 1817-1820; traveled to the South and the West Indies, 1821; and studied law with Judge Creed Taylor in Cumberland County, Virginia, 1822-1823. He began his law practice in Clarksburg, Virginia (later West Virginia), in 1824, and represented Harrison County in the House of Delegates, 1827-1830. He was a member of the Virginia Constitutional Convention of 1829-1830. He married Mary E. Willcox June, 1830, and moved to Petersburg, where he again was elected to the General Assembly, 1831-1836. He was a delegate to the national convention of the Republican (now Democratic) Party, but died on 20 November 1836, at his father's home, Otter Hills, after a brief illness.
    The first two letters in Box 14 date from the period of his attendance at New London Academy; then follow the papers relating to Princeton, where he matriculated in 1817 at the age of 19. He was placed in the Sophomore Class on the basis of an examination before the faculty, and received the highest mark given at the College, in each of the three years he spent at the College. His report sheets show the requirements for entrance, lists of courses, and contain a resolution passed by the trustees which condemned the sharp practices of the merchants in town.
    Some of the correspondence of John Thompson Brown with his brother-in-law Dr. William B. Steptoe in this period is interesting for the comments it contains on the Missouri question and other matters then being debated in the U.S. Senate. The remarks made by John Thompson Brown in letters from his collegiate period may be compared with his statements on the subject of slavery later made on the floor of the House of Delegates.
    After graduating from Princeton, John Thompson Brown traveled to the South, and made a brief trip to the West Indies, keeping notes on his impressions. Upon his return he took up the study of law with Judge Taylor. From this period come interesting musings on such subjects as "the family fireside," "youthful recollection," "friendship," and "behavior of a lawyer if he is to succeed." His license to practice law, dated 7 March 1824, is included in the collection. He journeyed to Clarksburg, Virginia, to set up his law practice, and kept a notebook on the trip West which reveal his first impressions of the Clarksburg area.
    At the end of this box is a scrapbook containing some of his published writings, speeches, and newspaper articles.
    - James H. Otey, Mount Prospect, to John [Thompson] Brown, 6 December 1816. (Box-folder 14:1)
      Letter from a schoolboy friend regarding New London Academy.
    - Ann T. Brown to her brother, Henry Brown, in Franklin County, [1816]. (Box-folder 14:2)
      John Thompson Brown's examinations at the New London Academy.
    - John [Thompson Brown], Princeton, New Jersey, to Henry Brown, 4 November 1817. (Box-folder 14:3)
      "I have just been examined by the faculty and am admitted to the Sophomore Class, which is the second in the college." His expenses are estimated at $200.00 for the first term and $90.00 for the second. "I will pledge myself not to spend one cent more than is really necessary."
    - Dr. William B. Steptoe, New London, to his brother-in-law, John Thompson Brown, November-December 1817., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 14:4)
      News from home; a rumor that some boys were expelled from Chapel Hill for their politics.
    - Dr. William B. Steptoe, New London, to John Thompson Brown, January-November 1818., 6 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 14:5)
      Medical advice; a suggested teacher for New London Academy ("Has he energy enough manage southern students?"); the death of Polly [Mrs. Mary Brown Clayton], sister of John Thompson Brown.
    - Dr. William B. Steptoe, New London, to John Thompson Brown, 21 March 1818. (Box-folder 14:6)
      The political upheaval at William and Mary College; deputies appointed "...to fix upon the site of the Virginia University."
    - John Thompson Brown, Princeton, to his father, Henry Brown, May-October 1818., 4 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 14:7)
      "My expenses have far exceeded what was necessary or what you expect. I now see my error and repent..." Three months later he offers to leave school because of his additional debts. Later in Baltimore, he is robbed of $200.00. His father adds up the year's expenses to a total of $670.00.
    - Report of John Thompson Brown of the sophomore class, Princeton, New Jersey, to Henry Brown, 29 September 1818. (Box-folder 14:8)
      Behavior, No. 1. distinguished; Industry, No. 1. distinguished; Scholarship, No. 1. distinguished (1) "If under the article scholarship, a student is marked No. 1 distinguished (1), he is considered as ranking among the first in his class." (From printed explanation of the report.)
    - James H. Otey, Chapel Hill, North Carolina, to John Thompson Brown, January-September 1819., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 14:9)
      "Once the busy scene of commercial enterprise...now lifeless and inactive." Concerning Lynchburg.
    - Dr. William B. Steptoe, New London, to John Thompson Brown, January-December 1819., 5 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 14:10)
      The University of Virginia is established at Charlottesville with an annual appropriation of $15,000; news of a threat of slave uprisings in Fredericksburg.
    - Report of John Thompson Brown of the junior class at Princeton, New Jersey to Henry Brown, 14 April, 29 September 1819., 2 reports. PDS. (Box-folder 14:11)
      Similar reports to that of 1818. Warning is added to the September report concerning excessive expenditures by students: "the trustees of the college give this notice to the parents and guardians of the youth, that they ought to pay no debt contracted in this town, which they have not specifically authorized."
    - List of the names of members of the class, n.d. (Box-folder 14:12)
      Endorsed: "Collegians mei consocui." He knew 162 fellow students.
    - John Thompson Brown, Princeton, to Dr. William B. Steptoe, 28 January 1820. (Box-folder 14:13)
      On the "present session of Congress."
    - J. H. Otey, Chapel Hill, to John Thompson Brown, January-May 1820., 4 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 14:14)
      Rumor of a great rebellion that has taken place at Princeton; the Missouri question.